Guide to the Richard Protovin Papers MSS.451
Fales Library and Special Collections
Richard Protovin Papers
1969-2003
1975-1986
Fales Library and Special Collections
Protovin, Richard
MSS.451
3 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons
Richard Potovin (June 5, 1945 - December 6, 1991) was a painter, filmmaker, and art teacher. He founded and headed the animation department at NYU’s Tisch School of the Arts, where he was an associate professor from 1979 to 1988, before joining the faculty at University of Tampa. The Richard Protovin Papers include published and unpublished materials created and collected by Richard Protovin including his animation cels, manuscript proofs, diaries, day books, and NYU tenure report. The collection also contains a small amount of materials about Protovin, such as newspaper articles.
Scope and Contents
The Richard Protovin Papers include published and unpublished materials created and collected by Richard Protovin. Materials created by Protovin include a copy of his master's thesis, personal diaries, day planners, animation cels for various works, a storyboard book for the short film Southern Images, and proofs for the unpublished children's books Turtle Pond, Flight of the Duckoes and The Land of Turtle Play. Other materials in the collection include his NYU faculty tenure report, catalogs from several exhibitions on Protovin’s paintings, a book of artwork created by his students, and a book from the NYU animation faculty celebrating the beginning of his year-long sabbatical. The collection also contains a small amount of materials about Protovin, such as newspaper articles.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections. Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical / Historical
Richard Potovin (June 5, 1945 - December 6, 1991) was a painter, filmmaker and art teacher who founded and headed the animation department at NYU’s Tisch School of the Arts, where he was an associate professor from 1979 to 1988. In 1988, he moved to Florida to work at the University of Tampa as a professor of animation production and cinema studies. Protovin died in 1991 from AIDS-related illness.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Jody Hensley in March of 2016. The accession number associated with this gift is 2016.009.
Artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Animation.; Animation cels.
- Animation Cels: Untitled, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Animation Cels: Dickey Boat #3, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Animation Cels: E Duck #4, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Animation Cels: Straw PIB 2101-2400, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Animation Cels: Fem Film 961-1040, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Animation Cels: UU #19, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Animation Cels: Frihouse #7, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Animation Cels: Fan Film 401-480, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Animation Cels: Blue River 800 - 1000, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Animation Cels: Untitled, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Animation Cels: Manhattan (Animation), 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Animation Cels: Blue River 2400-2600, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Animation Cels: Flamingo Bogg 2200-2371, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Animation Cels: Blue River 1400-1600, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Animation Cels: Untitled, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Diaries, Notebooks, Scrapbooks, 1975-1986 (Box 2)
- NYU Tenure Report, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
- Film Show Materials, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
- Masters Thesis, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Art Shows for Paintings, 1993-2003 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Newspaper Articles, 1991-2001 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Dedication Book from Students, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Southern Images Proof, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)